<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://songolt.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://songolt.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-30T03:46:04-05:00</updated><id>https://songolt.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Songolt</title><subtitle>Data Science for Mongolia's Future</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Announcing Songolt.org</title><link href="https://songolt.org/accouncement/2020/07/30/Announcing-Songolt-org.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Announcing Songolt.org" /><published>2020-07-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://songolt.org/accouncement/2020/07/30/Announcing-Songolt-org</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://songolt.org/accouncement/2020/07/30/Announcing-Songolt-org.html">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-07-30-Announcing-Songolt-org.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi, I'm &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RobertERitz&quot;&gt;Robert Ritz&lt;/a&gt;, a Data Scientist and educator based in Mongolia. Welcome to Songolt.org, a place for datasets, analyses, and tools to support Mongolia's democracy and civil society. I built Songolt because I believe that data science has huge potential to support Mongolia and its citizens. In this post I want to explain my motivation for creating Songolt, what you can expect from this site going forward, and how you can expect this site to be transparent at all levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;The-Motivation-Behind-Songolt&quot;&gt;The Motivation Behind Songolt&lt;a class=&quot;anchor-link&quot; href=&quot;#The-Motivation-Behind-Songolt&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Situated between Russia and China, Mongolia is a shining light of democracy in a sea of authoritarianism after a peaceful democratic revolution in 1990. Rich in natural resources, it is the only country in Central Asia ranked &lt;em&gt;Free&lt;/em&gt; by Freedom House. But Mongolia's democracy is still young, and its civil society is still being developed. Mongolia has no lack of challenges today and in the future. It faces economic challenges like increasing debt and fluctuating commodity prices that have caused boom and bust cycles in years past. Developmental challenges with regards to the disparity of living conditions between high-rise city dwellers, those living in poorly planned &quot;ger districts&quot;, and nomadic herders. Corruption remains an ever present reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, these challenges are not unique to Mongolia. while not unique, these challenges are complex and, in todays information age, regularly involve lots of data. Civil society organizations, journalists, and concerned citizens usually do not have the technical resources or time to tackle many of these issues. With the rise of data science over the past several years, we now have tools and techniques that can help illuminate these challenges, and perhaps even propose solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been working in this area for some time in Mongolia. My first attempt was when I started &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/mongolian-data-stories&quot;&gt;Mongolian Data Stories&lt;/a&gt;, a Medium publication that uses data stories to provide insight into issues and challenges in Mongolia. I thought that by building inspiring data stories journalists and civil society would be able to follow along and produce their own unique data stories. Indeed, I found that there were many that wanted to create stories in this way, but there was often a skills gap or they simply did not have the time to devote to finding, cleaning, and analyzing the data behind these stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Songolt aims to be a bridge between the data and those who are charged with preserving and defending Mongolia's democracy, journalists and civil society organizations. Data science is uniquely suited to this type of work. Unlike traditional areas of science, data science does not solely live in academic journals or at universities. It lives all around us and must be able to be understood by all relevant stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;What-to-Expect-from-Songolt&quot;&gt;What to Expect from Songolt&lt;a class=&quot;anchor-link&quot; href=&quot;#What-to-Expect-from-Songolt&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be three things you can expect to see on Songolt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Datasets&lt;/strong&gt; - Valuable data is often locked in a database, public facing government system, or scanned PDF documents. Often all that is needed is some data to get the conversation going. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyses&lt;/strong&gt; - Issues like the current COVID-19 pandemic involve complex and ever changing data. The government rarely releases coherent analyses, instead relying on summary statistics with little context. Current, reliable analyses are sometimes needed to support a rational and fact based discussion. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tools&lt;/strong&gt; - Sometimes an issue will remain relevant over time or will be more complex than a static analysis can explain. In these situations a tool can often be the best way for journalists to discover insights in an unbiased way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By releasing difficult to obtain datasets, creating analyses of complex issues, and releasing tools that will allow self-service discovery of insights, I hope that this bridge will be enough to allow valuable discussions to occur. Initially there will be &lt;strong&gt;one to two posts a month&lt;/strong&gt;, each being a dataset, analysis, or tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each post will relate to a pressing need in Mongolia today. Occasionally related posts will be spaced out and comprise a larger project over time. For example I may release a dataset and then build a tool from it later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Committment-to-Openness&quot;&gt;Committment to Openness&lt;a class=&quot;anchor-link&quot; href=&quot;#Committment-to-Openness&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Openness will be at the heart of everything on Songolt. Every dataset, analysis, and tool will be released to the public for free. There will be no pay wall, no subscription fee, and no private content. All code will also be released to the public under a license that will allow free re-use for any purpose. This site itself is hosted in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robertritz/songolt-org&quot;&gt;public repository&lt;/a&gt;, where all posts can be downloaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, my hope is that this openness will go both ways. If you have an idea or a challenge relevant to Songolt, please reach out to me. If you are a journalist or NGO, &lt;em&gt;definitely reach out&lt;/em&gt;. I also, understand that journalists work on &quot;getting a scoop&quot;, and I'm sensitive to that. I can delay publishing until after your story is published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If any journalist, NGO, or citizen has questions about the work on this site, please no not hesitate to contact me. I can be reached at robertritz@outlook.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Support-Songolt.org&quot;&gt;Support Songolt.org&lt;a class=&quot;anchor-link&quot; href=&quot;#Support-Songolt.org&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the work on Songolt is done on my own time. I'm committed to working on one to two posts a month, but with your support I could do even more. Hosting datasets and server costs for tools is also a significant cost over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support the creation of analysis, data, and tools for Mongolian civil society by becoming a supporter on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/songolt&quot;&gt;Patreon&lt;/a&gt;. By becoming a supporter you will allow for the work here to continue and get access to patron benefits. Patrons get mentioned on the site as a supporter and get access to a monthly Q&amp;amp;A where you can ask data and data science-related questions. For those that want a say in the direction of Songolt and what gets posted, All-Access patrons also get to vote on future projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://songolt.org/images/cover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://songolt.org/images/cover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mongolian Electoral District Demographic Analysis</title><link href="https://songolt.org/tools/election/2020/06/15/Mongolian-Electoral-District-Demographic-Analysis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mongolian Electoral District Demographic Analysis" /><published>2020-06-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://songolt.org/tools/election/2020/06/15/Mongolian-Electoral-District-Demographic-Analysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://songolt.org/tools/election/2020/06/15/Mongolian-Electoral-District-Demographic-Analysis.html">&lt;p&gt;The current election saw a switch back to the block voting system used in 1992 and 2008. This system has both &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ubc.ca/mongolia/2019/plurality-at-large-voting-revisited-for-2020/&quot;&gt;positives and negatives&lt;/a&gt;, and this system has much larger election districts than the previous single-member districts of the 2016 election. This allows us to more easily analyze the districts with the available data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put all of the data together and make it user friendly, I built &lt;a href=&quot;https://election.songolt.org&quot;&gt;election.songolt.org&lt;/a&gt;, an interactive data explorer that allows the reader to see key indicators of election districts. The indicators covered in the app include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Population indicators: population, household size, herder percent, age group breakdown&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Economic indicators (self-reported): salary, household loans, employment, education levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality of life indicators: crime, house type, toilet &amp;amp; water type, heating type
The data was collected from &lt;a href=&quot;1212.mn&quot;&gt;1212.mn&lt;/a&gt; and also the &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.nso.mn/nada/index.php/catalog/115&quot;&gt;Household Socioeconomic Survey of 2016&lt;/a&gt;, which is the latest survey that contains precise geographic labeling. Both data sources are maintained by the National Statistics Office of Mongolia.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several themes developed through my research into this data. These themes are perhaps not surprising for many readers familiar with Mongolia, but it is never a bad thing to back up observations with data. I encourage you, the reader, to explore the app yourself (&lt;a href=&quot;https://election.songolt.org&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;), but below I give an overview of the themes for your convenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ulaanbaatar-vs-countryside&quot;&gt;Ulaanbaatar vs Countryside&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the best-known difference in Mongolia is that of Ulaanbaatar and the countryside. The image of busy urban Ulaanbaatar juxtaposed with the bucolic countryside could hardly be more different. Indeed the data shows significant differences in many areas. Let’s compare the population pyramid for the election district with the highest population, Songinokhairkhan District in Ulaanbaatar, with the least populace, Bulgan Aimag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://songolt.org/images/electoral-district-analysis/population-pyramid.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an obvious population difference, but the size of the age groups also shows a marked difference between the two. Where you have a large spike in the 20–40 age group in Songinokhairkhan, Bulgans’ age groups have much less variability and are quite flat from 15–50. You will see a similar trend in the highest population election districts compared with the least populated ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means the voting demographics in rural areas are more widely distributed than in urban areas. D.Byambjav and E.Gerelt-Od &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ubc.ca/mongolia/2020/voter-demography/&quot;&gt;previously discussed&lt;/a&gt; the large and less engaged block of voters under 35. If youth engagement initiatives are successful, this block of voters will be less powerful in rural districts that have a similar age distribution to Bulgan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://songolt.org/images/electoral-district-analysis/population-unemployed.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employment differs significantly as well between Ulaanbaatar and most rural districts. Rural election districts tend to show significantly higher rates of overall employment than the urban ones. In the chart above, the “employed percentage” refers to the proportion of the working-age population that is employed. Urban districts tend to have between 45–55% employment, with rural districts between 65–75%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://songolt.org/images/electoral-district-analysis/average-salary.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salaries are also significantly higher in Ulaanbaatar. The salaries shown above are self-reported from 2016, but they show a very clear picture. Employment levels may be higher in rural areas, but salary levels are conversely lower. This is an obvious area where the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ubc.ca/mongolia/2020/guest-post-economic-policy-party-platforms/&quot;&gt;economic policy of the party platforms&lt;/a&gt; could address these inequalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;outliers-mining-areas-and-bayan-ulgii&quot;&gt;Outliers: Mining Areas and Bayan-Ulgii&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ulaanbaatar vs countryside theme may be the biggest theme in the data, it doesn’t give the full picture. There are two sets of outliers that “buck the trend”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is that the two primary mining areas of Mongolia, Erdenet (in Orkhon) and Oyu Toloig (in Umnugovi), show significantly higher salaries, lower loan rates, and higher educations than other rural election districts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://songolt.org/images/electoral-district-analysis/household-loans.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bubble plot shows the percent of households with loans vs monthly average salaries in each election district. The two highlighted in red are Orkhon (lower right) and Umnugovi (upper left). All of the bubbles above 550k average monthly salary except for the two in red are located in Ulaanbaatar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two election districts (and the urban workforce where the company offices are) have benefited heavily from the mining industry of Mongolia. Industrialization as proposed in the party platforms would most likely further benefit these areas, as this is where the raw materials would come from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://songolt.org/images/electoral-district-analysis/household-loans2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second outlier is Bayan-Ulgii. In the chart above, the red bubble to the farthest left is Bayan-Ulgii, and the red bubble on the far right is Khan-Uul District. The average household size is 5.2, significantly larger than the most populace district Songinokhairkhan of 3.8. Besides larger family sizes, Bayan-Ulgii has the lowest average monthly salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ulaanbaatar-districts-have-diverse-needs&quot;&gt;Ulaanbaatar Districts Have Diverse Needs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The districts of Ulaanbaatar also show diverse needs. Every district also contains part of the ger district. This means that there is a mix of urban and peri-urban in every election district of Ulaanbaatar. In the center of the city, households are connected to the central water, heating, and sewage systems. In the ger district, living standards become sharply different, with no central heat or water connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://songolt.org/images/electoral-district-analysis/heating-type.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unique layout of the city districts ensures that at least 20% of the population of each district uses pit toilets and wood or coal for heat. More than 40% of Khan-Uul district households, the most affluent election district in Mongolia, use ordinary wood and coal stoves for heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mps-will-represent-very-diverse-groups&quot;&gt;MPs Will Represent Very Diverse Groups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the outcome of the election, it is clear that the needs of citizens in election districts are not uniform, and even the common trope of UB vs the rest doesn’t hold up completely. Even though Mongolia a small country with a heavy focus on mining, it isn’t clear that the party platforms address the inequalities mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the economics platforms of the DP, MPP, and Right Person Electorate all &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ubc.ca/mongolia/2020/guest-post-economic-policy-party-platforms/&quot;&gt;focus on heavy industry&lt;/a&gt;, it isn’t clear how heavy industry would help rural areas outside of the main mining areas lacking in high paying jobs, or whether it would increase employment levels in Ulaanbaatar.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><summary type="html">The current election saw a switch back to the block voting system used in 1992 and 2008. This system has both positives and negatives, and this system has much larger election districts than the previous single-member districts of the 2016 election. This allows us to more easily analyze the districts with the available data.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://songolt.org/images/electoral-district-analysis/cover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://songolt.org/images/electoral-district-analysis/cover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>